Hi and welcome back. In a previous lecture we have seen how giving MCP server a broad access to a back-end services
could lead to a broken authorization vulnerabilities and in a specific to a confused duty attack.
Today we will explore another common vulnerability in AI applications which is called the prompt injection.
We will be using a customer chatbot application to demonstrate this attack.
The chatbot is powered by AI and it's supposed to help customers with the problems related to their orders.
For simplicity I created the chatbot application as a command line application.
In real world the support chatbot typically would be a web-based application.
Also to keep things simple in the chatbot application source code I heart-coded the default customer ID to be customer number one.
This is for simplicity. In real world again the customer identity is identified through authentication mechanisms.
The whole idea here is to focus about the prompt injection attack and avoid complexity with implementing authentication.
Let's go with the data flow a little bit. So the chatbot takes the customers' questions and then it append them to a prompt template.
Then it sends the prompt to an AI model hosted in LM Studio.
We are using LM Studio here for simplicity and real world companies would probably be using enterprise grade AI models.
The prompt itself instructs the AI model to generate an SQL query based on the customer input or customer question.
The SQL query is supposed to query the back-end database in order to get information about the customer's orders.
So once the chatbot gets the SQL query from the AI model it pass this SQL query to an MCP server tool called search database.
The search database is going to execute the SQL query against the back-end database.
And once we have the response from the database it's passed again to AI model in order to generate a human friendly response which is supposed to help customers with their problems.
Now notice here that the SQL query itself it was generated by the AI model based on a prompt that contains customer's input.
And just like any security vulnerability anything built on user input can lead to a security problems.
Let's have a look at the code snippet that builds the prompt from the user input.
If you open the chatbot up script file and navigate to generate SQL with LLM method here.
We can see the prompt template defined under this method.
The prompt instructs the AI model to help in generating a Postgres SQL statement.
It asks to only retire SQL statement without any explanation, back-text or comments.
We can also see that it hardcoded the user identity to be customer one.
And this is the part that I said before.
For demonstration purposes we are hard coding the customer identity in a set of building you know like authentication logic.
Where in real-world the customer identity should come from authentication session like cookie or authorization token.
We can also see that the prompt provides the database schema to the AI model so it can know which tables and columns exist.
Finally the prompt appends the user query here.
Let's see this chatbot in action and play with it a little bit.
So I have my Docker compose up and running which will start the MCP server as well as the Postgres database.
I also have the LLM Studio running locally on port 1, 2, 3, 4 and all what I need to do is to start the chatbot script.
And as soon as I do that we should see some logs in the LLM Studio.
So let me go ahead and start this and to verify we should see some logs in the LLM Studio part and this should be under the developer tab.
So the chatbot starts with sample equations that a customer might ask.
I'm going to copy and paste one of those questions so let's go maybe with the second one to show me all my pending orders.
And we can see that I added some verbose logging in order to see the generated SQL queries the interaction with LLM Studio with the MCP in real time.
By the way, we should also see some real time logs on the LLM Studio part and that happens under the developer tab.
Okay, back to our chatbot.
We can see it first connected to the LLM Studio and then the LLM Studio generated this SQL query.
We can see it says to select everything from order stable where the customer ID is the one that we hardcoded and a filter that says order status is pending,
which is like a pretty basic SQL query.
Then our chatbot passed that to the MCP server to execute this SQL.
It retrieved the raw result from the database and then passed those into LLM Studio in order to do some formatting.
To map this really quick back to our diagram, the chatbot took the customer or the user query,
appended that into a prompt template and then passed it to the LLM Studio to generate SQL query.
Once we have the SQL query, the chatbot passed that to the MCP server to execute that in the DB and then the response.
Again, it passed it to LLM Studio to have to have a formatted output and then the output is passed back to the user or to the customer.
At this point, the chatbot is working as expected.
And I don't want to make this video too long, so I will leave it to you to explore the chatbot functionality further.
And see if you can access data that you are not authorized to access.
In the next lecture, we will inject the prompt to access data that belongs to another users or another customers.
But we will also discuss how to mitigate those prompt injection vulnerabilities.
I hope that this lecture has been informative for you and I hope to see you in the next one.
Thanks for watching.